<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="0913000100.xml" version="5.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letters patent. <date when="1532-03-15">17 March, 1532</date></title>
                <editor>
                    <name type="person">Mike Jones</name>
                    <email>mike.a.jones@me.com</email>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>http://bristollia.org</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>
                <date when="2014-10">December 2014</date>
                <idno type="UUID">e5b052a60-c62e-4d47-b515-d31a4cca7f7b</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Bristol</settlement>
                        <repository>Bristol Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>40715/Ad/1/1</idno>
                        <msName>Bristol Grammer School Charter</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p></p>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Thorne</item>
                        <item>St Bartholomew's</item>
                        <item>Bristol</item>
                        <item>Gloucestershire</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="text" xml:lang="la">
                <p><hi rend="bold">Henricus Octavus Dei gracia Anglie et Francie Rex</hi> <lb/>
                ffidei defensor et dominus hibernie <hi rend="bold">Omnibus</hi> ad quos
                presentes littere pervenerint. Salutem. <hi rend="bold">Sciatis</hi> 
                <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> nos considerantes pium propositum 
                <expan>dilector<ex>um</ex></expan> nobis Thome West militis domini <lb/>
                la Warr Georgii Croft Capellani <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ri</expan> Roberti
                Thorne Nicholei Thorne Ville <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>e</expan> Bristollie et
                Johannis Godryche clerici executoris testamenti Roberti Thorne defuncti
                in fundacione <expan>continuac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> <lb/> et
                <expan>supportac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> cuiusdam Scole gramaticalis
                in <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a</expan> Villa Bristollie aut in 
                suburbiis eiusdem Ville pro pueris in eadem Scola erudiendis in bonis 
                moribis et <expan>litteratur<ex>is</ex></expan> pro meliori 
                <expan>sustentac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> <lb/> unious magistri et
                unius hostiarii sive <expan>duor<ex>um</ex></expan> 
                <expan>hostiarior<ex>um</ex></expan> eisudem et <expan>aliar<ex>um</ex></expan>
                rerum <expan>necessariar<ex>um</ex></expan> ibidem 
                <expan>faciend<ex>i</ex></expan> ac gracia <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan>
                speciali ac ex certa sciencia et mero moti <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ris</expan>
                concessimus et <lb/> licenciam dedimus ac per presentes concedimus et
                licenciam damus pro nobis et heredibus et heredibus
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ris</expan> quantum in nobis est maiori burgensibus
                et commutati <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>e</expan> Ville Bristollie et
                successoribus <lb/> suis <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> ipsi et sucessores sui
                acquiere et recipere possint domum sive hospitale sanct Bartholomei in
                <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>e</expan> villa <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan>
                Bristollie <expan>d<ex>o</ex>m<ex>in</ex>a</expan> maneria mesuagia
                <expan>t<ex>er</ex>ras</expan> tenementa Gardina pomaria <lb/>
                <expan>prat<ex>a</ex></expan> <expan>past<ex>uras</ex></expan> 
                <expan>pastur<ex>as</ex></expan> <expan>reddit<ex>us</ex></expan>
                reveriones servicia cum omnibus suis iuribus proficuis et
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>oditatibus</expan> que nunc sunt aut aliquo
                tempore preterito <expan>accept<ex>um</ex></expan> sive
                <expan>reputat<ex>um</ex></expan> fuerunt ut <expan>parcell<ex>a</ex></expan>
                euisdem <lb/> hospitalis aut que <expan>pred<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>us</expan>
                Georgius Croft magister hospitalis <expan>predict<ex>i</ex></expan>
                habuit tenuit aut gavisus fuit in iure eiusdem hospitalis tam in
                <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a</expan> villa Bristollie 
                <expan>q<ex>ua</ex>m</expan> in parchocia de Clyfton <lb/>
                Stapulton Godbury <note>Sodbury?</note> et Wyckewarr in 
                <expan>Com<ex>itatu</ex></expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro</expan>
                <expan>Gloucestr<ex>ie</ex></expan> seu alibi in
                <expan>Com<ex>itatu</ex></expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro</expan>
                <expan>Gloucestr<ex>ie</ex></expan> sei alibi in 
                <expan>com<ex>itatu</ex></expan> <expan>pred<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>e</expan>
                Ville <expan>Bristoll<ex>ie</ex></expan> <expan>Glouc<ex>estrie</ex></expan>
                aut alibi infra <expan>Regnu<ex>m</ex></expan>
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>r<ex>u</ex>m</expan> Anglie ad <expan>annuu<ex>m</ex></expan>
                valorem quadraginta <expan>librar<ex>um</ex></expan> ultra <lb/>
                <expan>om<ex>n</ex>ia</expan> onera et reprisas tam de prefato Thoma West milite
                domino laWarr vero patrono et fundatore hospitalis <expan>predict<ex>i</ex></expan>
                <expan>q<ex>ua</ex>m</expan> de <expan>predict<ex>o</ex></expan> Georgio
                Crofte magistro ac <expan>custod<ex>e</ex></expan> domus sive hospitalis
                <expan>predict<ex>i</ex></expan> et de fratribus et sororibus eiusdem domus
                sive hospitalis vel de <expan>eor<ex>um</ex></expan> aliquo aut de quibuscumque
                aliis <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sonis</expan> habentes sive habere
                <expan>pretendent<ex>es</ex></expan> aut imposterum aliquo tempore habere
                contigerit aliquod ius titulum aut <lb/> possessionem usum vel intresse de et
                in premissis vel aliqua inde <expan>p<ex>ar</ex>cella</expan> licet de nobis in
                capite vel <expan>alit<ex>er</ex></expan> aut de aliis <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sonis</expan>
                vel <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sona</expan> mediate vel immedediate teneantur
                <hi rend="bold">habendua</hi> <note>habenda?</note> sibi et successoribus suis
                imperpetuum. Et <lb/> eidem <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sone</expan> siue eisdem
                <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> ipsi <expan>domu<ex>m</ex></expan> siue hospitale
                <expan>p<ex>re</ex>dict<ex>am</ex></expan> <expan>d<ex>o</ex>m<ex>anic</ex>a</expan>
                maneria <expan>t<ex>er</ex>ras</expan> et tenementa ac cetera premissa cum suis 
                <expan>pertin<ex>enciis</ex></expan> Maiori Burgensibus et 
                <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>unitati</expan> Ville <expan>predict<ex>e</ex></expan> et
                Succesoribus <lb/> suis <expan>p<ex>re</ex>dict<ex>us</ex></expan> as
                <expan>annuu<ex>m</ex></expan> valorem <expan>predict<ex>um</ex></expan> in
                forma <expan>pred<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a</expan> dare concedere legare vel
                assignare possunt et valeant. Similiter licenciam dedimus et concessimus
                ac damus concedimus specialem per presentes <expan>Absq<ex>ue</ex></expan> <lb/>
                impedimento impeticione seu grauamine <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ri</expan> 
                <expan>hered<ex>um</ex></expan> vel successorum 
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro<ex>rum</ex></expan> <expan>Justic<ex>iariorum</ex></expan>
                <expan>Escaeto<ex>rum</ex></expan> Vicecomitum <expan>Ballivor<ex>um</ex></expan>
                seu <expan>alio<ex>rum</ex></expan> <expan>Ministro<ex>rum</ex></expan>
                <expan>quo<ex>rum</ex>cumq<ex>ue</ex></expan> Volumus insuper et concedimus per
                presentes eisdem Maiori et <lb/> Burgensibus et <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>unitati</expan>
                Ville Bristollie <expan>predict<ex>e</ex></expan> et Successoribus suis 
                <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> ipsi et successores sui <expan>H<ex>ab</ex>eant</expan>
                et obtineant aut <expan>h<ex>ab</ex>ere</expan> et obtinere possint tam presentes
                <expan>l<ex>itt</ex>ras</expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ras</expan> patentes
                <expan>q<ex>ua</ex>m</expan> omnia et <expan>om<ex>n</ex>imoda</expan> breuia ac <lb/>
                <expan>l<ex>itt</ex>ras</expan> regias executorias et confirmatorias in hac parte
                de tempore in tempus <expan>f<ex>ac</ex>iend<ex>o</ex></expan> et 
                <expan>exequend<ex>o</ex></expan>. <expan>Absq<ex>ue</ex></expan> aliquo seu feodo
                inde in Cancellaria <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan> <expan>hered<ex>um</ex></expan>
                vel <expan>succesor<ex>um</ex></expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro<ex>rum</ex></expan>
                sue in hanaperio eiusdem Cancellaria <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan> aut alibi <lb/>
                quoquo modo <expan>taxand<ex>o</ex></expan> imponendum 
                <expan>f<ex>ac</ex>iend<ex>o</ex></expan> <expan>solvend<ex>o</ex></expan>
                siue <expan>capiend<ex>o</ex></expan> Et <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> siue
                <expan>Cl<ex>er</ex>icus</expan> Hanapii <expan>predict<ex>i</ex></expan>
                aut eius deputatus ibidem <expan>p<ex>ro</ex></expan> tempore existens inde
                quietus et in Compto suo ad <expan>S<ex>ca</ex>cc<ex>ariu</ex>m</expan>
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro<ex>rum</ex></expan> <expan>reddend<ex>o</ex></expan> <lb/>
                exonerati existant <expan>imperpetuu<ex>m</ex></expan> Statuto de
                <expan>ter<ex>ris</ex></expan> et <expan>ten<ex>ementis</ex></expan> ad
                <expan>manu<ex>m</ex></expan> mortuam non ponendum Aut aliquibus aliis statutus
                actibus ordinacionibus restrictionibus siue mandatis
                <expan>incontrar<ex>iu</ex>m</expan> <expan>fac<ex>tis</ex></expan>
                <expan>edit<ex>is</ex></expan> siue <expan>ordinat<ex>is</ex></expan> aut
                <expan>f<ex>ac</ex>iend<ex>is</ex></expan> siue <expan>ordinand<ex>is</ex></expan>.
                Aut <lb/> aliqua alia causa re vel <expan>mat<ex>er</ex>ia</expan>
                <expan>quacumq<ex>ue</ex></expan> non <expan>obstan<ex>tibus</ex></expan>.
                Et <expan>absq<ex>ue</ex></expan> aliquo breui seu breuibus 
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ris</expan> <expan>hered<ex>um</ex></expan> vel
                <expan>successor<ex>um</ex></expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro<ex>rum</ex></expan>
                de ad quod <expan><ex>dampnum</ex></expan> <expan>p<ex>ro</ex></expan>
                premissis vel aliquo <expan>premissor<ex>um</ex></expan>
                <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>sequend<ex>o</ex></expan> vel 
                <expan>f<ex>ac</ex>iend<ex>o</ex></expan> <hi rend="bold">Aut</hi> eo
                <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> expressa mentio de <lb/> certitudine
                <expan>premisso<ex>rum</ex></expan> seu de aliis donis siue concessionibus
                per nos aut aliquem <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>genito<ex>rum</ex></expan>
                <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ro<ex>rum</ex></expan> <expan>p<ex>re</ex>fatis</expan>
                Maiori Burgensibus et <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>unitati</expan> Ville
                <expan>predict<ex>e</ex></expan> et succesoribus suis antea
                <expan>fact<ex>is</ex></expan> in <expan>p<ex>re</ex>sentibus</expan>
                <expan>l<ex>itt</ex>ris</expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ris</expan>
                patentibus <lb/> minime <expan>fact<ex>a</ex></expan> 
                <expan>exist<ex>it</ex></expan> in non <expan>obstant<ex>ibus</ex></expan>
                <hi rend="bold">In cuius</hi> rei testimonium has 
                <expan>l<ex>itt</ex>ras</expan> <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ras</expan>
                fieri ferimus patentes. <hi rend="bold">Teste</hi> me ipso apud Chelsehith
                decimo septime die Marcu Anno regni <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ri</expan>
                vicesimo tercio. <hi rend="bold">Popeley</hi> <lb/>
                Per <expan>br<ex>ev</ex>e</expan> de priuato sigillo et de data
                <expan>pred<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a</expan> auctoritate parliamenti
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>Henry the Eighth, by the grace of God, King of England and France, defender
                of the faith and lord of Ireland. To all those whom these present letters shall
                come. Greetings. Know that we considering the blessed purpose of our beloved
                to us Thomas West, knight, lord La Warr, George Croft our chaplain, Robert Thorne,
                Nicholas Thorne of our town of Bristol and John Godryche, clerk, executor of the
                will of Robert Thorne, deceased, in the foundation, continuation and support of
                a certain grammar school in the said town of Bristol or in the suburbs of the
                same town for children in the same school to be instructed in good customs
                and learning for the better maintenance of one master and one usher or two
                ushrs of the same and other things requisite in the same place made of our 
                special grace and our certain knowledge and mere motion we have granted and
                given license for us and our heirs in so far as we are able to the mayor,
                burgesses and commonality of the saids town of Bristol and their successors
                that themselves and their successors be able to acquire and receive the
                house or hospital of Saint Bartholomew in our said town of Bristol, and the
                demense lands, manors, messuages, lands, tenements, gardens, orchards, meadows,
                pastures, pastures, rents, reversions, services with all their rights, profits
                and advantages which are now or any time past have been accepted or considered
                or parcel of the same hospital or which the said George Croft master of the said
                hospital had held or was enjoying in right of the same hospital in the said
                town of Bristol and in the parish of Clyfton, Stapulton, Sodbury and Wyckwarr
                in our county of Gloucestershire or elsewhere in the county of the said town
                of Bristol of Gloucestershire or elsewhere within our kindom of England to
                the yearly value of forty pounds over and above all charges and deductions both
                of the said Thomas West knight lord La Warr true patron and founder of the
                said hospital and of the said George Crofte master and custodian of the said 
                house or hospital and of the brothers and sisters of the same house or hospital 
                or of any of them or of whichever other persons or person having or claiming 
                to have or anytime in the future should happen to have some right, title,
                possession, right or interest of and in the premisses or any parcel thereof
                although is held of us in chief or of other persons or person directly or
                indirectly; to be held to themselves in perpetuity. And the same person or
                persons that they themselves are able and can give, grant, bequeth or assign
                the said house or hospital, demense lands, manors, lands, tenements and other
                premisses with their appurtenances to the mayor, burgesses and commonality
                of the said town and their aforesaid successors to the said yearly value
                in the said form. Similarly we gave and granted and we give special licence
                by the presents without hinderance, claim or injury of our heirs or successors,
                of our justices, escheaters, sheriffs, bailiffs or of other our ministers
                whatsoever. As mentioned above we wish and grand by the presents to the same
                mayor and burgesses and commonality of the said town of Bristol and their
                successors that they their successors may have and possess or many they be able
                to have or possess both our present letters patent and all and every kind of
                writ and royal letters of execution and confirmation which is to be made
                and done from time to time. Without any fine or fee in whatever was taxed,
                imposed, made, paid or taken therefore in our Chancery, our heirs and successors,
                or in the Hanaper of the same our Chancery and elsewhere. And that the keeper
                or clerk of the aforesaid Hanaper or his deputy in the same place for the time
                being shall be quit thereof and shall be exonerated forever in their account
                which is to be returned to the Exchequer. The statutes of not putting lands
                and tenements in mortmain or any other statutes, acts, ordinances, restrictions
                or mandates made, proclaimed or ordained or which is to be made or ordained
                to the contrary or any other cause, thing or matter whatsoever not withstanding.
                And without other or writ or writs of <foreign xml:lang="la">ad quod 
                dampnum</foreign> <note>`to what damage'</note> our heirs and successors, which is 
                to be prosecuted or madefor the premisses or any premisses. Or that express mention 
                is not made on ourpresent letters patent of the certainty of the premisses or of 
                other gifts, concessions formerly made by us or other of our ancestors to the mayor,
                burgesses and commonality of the aforesaid town of Bristol and their
                successors, in anywise not withstanding. In witness of which thing we have
                caused these letters to be made patent. Witnessed by myself at Chelsea the
                seventeenth day of March the twenty third year of our reign. Popeley.
                By the writ of the privy seal and of the date aforesaid. By authority of
                Parliament.
            </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>