<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="0913000100.xml" version="5.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letters patent. <date when="1532-03-15">17 March, 1532</date></title>
                <editor>
                    <name type="person">Mike Jones</name>
                    <email>mike.a.jones@me.com</email>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>http://bristollia.org</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>
                <date when="2014-10">December 2014</date>
                <idno type="UUID">e5b052a60-c62e-4d47-b515-d31a4cca7f7b</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Bristol</settlement>
                        <repository>Bristol Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>40715/Ad/1/1</idno>
                        <msName>Bristol Grammer School Charter</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p></p>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Thorne</item>
                        <item>St Bartholomew's</item>
                        <item>Bristol</item>
                        <item>Gloucestershire</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Henricus Octavus Dei gracia Anglie et Francie Rex</hi> <lb/>
                ffidei defensor et dominus hibernie <hi rend="bold">Omnibus</hi> ad quos
                presentes littere pervenerint. Salutem. <hi rend="bold">Sciatis</hi> 
                <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> nos considerantes pium propositum 
                <expan>dilector<ex>um</ex></expan> nobis Thome West militis domini <lb/>
                la Warr Georgii Croft Capellani <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ri</expan> Roberti
                Thorne Nicholei Thorne Ville <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>e</expan> Bristollie et
                Johannis Godryche clerici executoris testamenti Roberti Thorne defuncti
                in fundacione <expan>continuac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> <lb/> et
                <expan>supportac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> cuiusdam Scole gramaticalis
                in <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a</expan> Villa Bristollie aut in 
                suburbiis eiusdem Ville pro pueris in eadem Scola erudiendis in bonis 
                moribis et <expan>litteratur<ex>is</ex></expan> pro meliori 
                <expan>sustentac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>e</expan> <lb/> unious magistri et
                unius hostiarii sive <expan>duor<ex>um</ex></expan> 
                <expan>hostiarior<ex>um</ex></expan> eisudem et <expan>aliar<ex>um</ex><expan>
                rerum <expan>necessariar<ex>um</ex></expan> ibidem 
                <expan>faciend<ex>i</ex></expan> ac gracia <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan>
                speciali ac ex certa sciencia et mero moti <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ris</expan>
                concessimus et <lb/> licenciam dedimus ac per presentes concedimus et
                licenciam damus pro nobis et heredibus et heredibus
                <expan>n<ex>ost<ex>ris<expan> quantum in nobis est maiori burgensibus
                et commutati <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex></expan> Ville Bristollie et
                successoribus <lb/> suis <expan>q<ex>uo</ex>d</expan> ipsi et sucessores sui
                acquiere et recipere possint domum sive hospitale sanct Bartholomei in
                <expan>d<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>e</expan> villa <expan>n<ex>ost</ex>ra</expan>
                Bristollie <expan>d<ex>o</ex>m<ex>in</ex>a</expan> maneria mesuagia
                <expan>t<ex>er</ex>ras</expan> tenementa Gardina pomaria <lb/>
                <expan>prat<ex>a</ex></expan> <expan>past<ex>uras</ex></expan> 
                <expan>pastur<ex>as</ex></expan> <expan>reddit<ex>us</ex></expan>
                reveriones servicia cum omnibus suis iuribus proficuis et
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>oditatibus</expan> que nunc sunt aut aliquo
                tempore preterito <expan>accept<ex>um</ex></expan> sive
                <expan>reputat<ex>um</ex></expan> fuerunt ut <expan>parcell<ex>a</ex></expan>
                euisdem <lb/></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>Henry the Eighth, by the grace of God, King of England and France, defender
                of the faith and lord of Ireland. To all those whom these present letters shall
                come. Greetings. Know that we considering the blessed purpose of our beloved
                to us Thomas West, knight, lord La Warr, George Croft our chaplain, Robert Thorne,
                Nicholas Thorne of our town of Bristol and John Godryche, clerk, executor of the
                will of Robert Thorne, deceased, in the foundation, continuation and support of
                a certain grammar school in the said town of Bristol or in the suburbs of the
                same town for children in the same school to be instructed in good customs
                and learning for the better maintenance of one master and one usher or two
                ushrs of the same and other things requisite in the same place made of our 
                special grace and our certain knowledge and mere motion we have granted and
                given license for us and our heirs in so far as we are able to the mayor,
                burgesses and commonality of the saids town of Bristol and their successors
                that themselves and their successors be able to acquire and receive the
                house or hospital of Saint Bartholomew in our said town of Bristol, and the
                demense lands, manors, messuages, lands, tenements, gardens, orchards, meadows,
                pastures, pastures, rents, reversions, services with all their rights, profits
                and advantages which are now or any time past have been accepted or considered
                or parcel of the same
            </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>