<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="0913000100.xml" version="5.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Bartholomew School. <date when="1546-10-15">1607</date></title>
                <editor>
                    <name type="person">Mike Jones</name>
                    <email>mike.a.jones@me.com</email>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>http://bristollia.org</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bristol</pubPlace>
                <date when="2015-02">February 2015</date>
                <idno type="UUID">2cfe296b-e4a6-43fb-94ab-0a66239039aa</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>London</settlement>
                        <repository>The National Archives</repository>
                        <idno>C 93/3/18</idno>
                        <msName>GLOUCESTERSHIRE: Bristol Subject: Bartholomew School</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p></p>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Bristol</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="text" xml:lang="en">
                <p><hi rend="bold">James</hi> by the grace of God kinge of England Scotland
                ffrance and Ireland defender of the faith etc. <hi rend="bold">To the</hi>
                <expan>Rev<ex>er</ex>end</expan> ffather in God John Bushopp <lb/> of Bristoll.
                And to our trustie and Welbeloved Sir George Snigge knight one of the Barons
                of our Exchequer, Sir Edward Gorges, Sir Thomas Seymor knight, <lb/>
                lawrence hyde Recorder of the Cittie of Bris[toll] Simon Robson Doctor of
                Dyvinitye Deane of Bristoll, ffrauncis James Doctor of Lawe Chaucelloe of the
                diocesse <lb/> of Bristoll, Richard Cordrington Esquire, Cr[...] Greene, Roberte
                Gulliford Batcherlors of Divinytie, John Adams, Thomas Hughes, Thomas Younge,
                John Tynte <lb/> Esquiers, James Buck William Meredith, Myles Jackson gent,
                Israell Gleson Bachelor of lawe, John Yonge ad Nicholas Hill gentlemen
                Greetinge. <hi rend="bold">Knowe yee</hi> <lb/> that we for the due
                <expan>execuc<ex>i</ex>on</expan> of a <expan>c<ex>er</ex>taine</expan>
                Statute made in the Highe Courte of Parliament houl[...] the Seaven and
                twentyeth daye of October in the three and fortyth yere <lb/> of the Raigne
                of our late Sister Queene Elizabeth decease[d] intituled An Acte to redresse
                the mysimployment of land <expan>good<ex>es</ex></expan> and 
                <expan>stock<ex>es</ex></expan> of money herefore gyven to <lb/> charitable
                uses. And haveinge Specyall truste and consid[eracion] in your approved
                fidelityes Wysedomes and <expan>discrec<ex>i</ex>ons</expan> have
                aucthorised you to be our <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>issioners</expan> <lb/>
                <hi rend="bold">And by</hi> these <expan>p<ex>re</ex>ent</expan> doe gyve
                unto you and to any fouer or more of you full power and aucthoritye to
                enquire aswell by the oathes of twelve lawfull <lb/> more of the Cittye of
                Bristoll and Countye of the same as by all other goode and lawfull wityes
                and meanes accordinge to the purporce and true meanynge of <lb/> the saide
                Statute, What landes <expan>tenement<ex>es</ex></expan>
                <expan>rent<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>an<ex>n</ex>uyties</expan>
                <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>fitt<ex>es</ex></expan>
                <expan>Hereditament<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>good<ex>es</ex></expan> 
                chattles money or <expan>stock<ex>es</ex></expan> of money, Have at any
                tyme or tymes heretofore bin gyven <lb/> lymitted appoynted or assigned
                by us or any of our <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>genitors</expan>, or by any other
                Well disposed <expan>p<ex>er</ex>son</expan> or <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sons</expan>,
                bodies pollitique or corporate, for the releife of aged ympotent and <lb/>
                poore people mayntenaunce of sicke and maymed souldiours or marryners,
                School[es] od learnynge, ffree Schooles or Schollers in universityes, repayre
                of <expan>Bridg<ex>es</ex></expan>, <expan>port<ex>es</ex></expan>, havens <lb/>
                Cawsewayes, Churches, <expan>Seabank<ex>es</ex></expan> or Highewayes,
                <expan>educac<ex>i</ex>on</expan> or ???pferm of
                <expan>Orphanc<ex>es</ex></expan>, reliefe stocke or
                <expan>maynten<ex>a</ex>nce</expan> for Howses of
                <expan>correct<ex>i</ex>on</expan>, marriadges of poore maydes, 
                <expan>supportac<ex>i</ex>on</expan> ayde <lb/> or helpe of younge tradesmen,
                <expan>handicraft<ex>es</ex>men</expan>, or <expan>p<ex>er</ex>sons</expan>
                decayed, Reliefe or <expan>redempc<ex>i</ex>on</expan> or 
                <expan>prison<ex>er</ex>s</expan> or Captives, or ayde or ease of any poore
                <expan>Inh<ex>ab</ex>itant<ex>es</ex></expan> concerninge payment of
                ffiffteenes <lb/> settinge out of Souldiours, or other taxes in any parryshe
                town or place Within our saide Cittye of Bristoll and Countye of the same.
                And of all and singuler the abuses misdemeanors <lb/> breaches of trust
                <expan>negligenc<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>mysimploym<ex>ent</ex></expan>
                not ymployinge conceallinge defraudinge misconvertinge or misgoverment of the
                same <expan>land<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>tenment<ex>es</ex></expan>
                <expan>rent<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>an<ex>n</ex>uyties</expan>
                <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>fitt<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>Hereditam<ex>ents</ex></expan>
                <lb/> <expan>good<ex>es</ex></expan> chattles money or
                <expan>Stock<ex>es</ex></expan> of money or any of them hereyofore given
                limitted appoynted or assigned to or for any the charitable and godlie uses
                before rehearsed <lb/> accordinge to the purporce and true meaninge of the
                saide Statute. <hi rend="bold">And uppon</hi> suche Inquyrie heareinge and
                examyninge thereof accordinge to the saide <lb/> Statute to Sett downe such
                orders Judgment and decrees as the saide landes
                <expan>tenement<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>rent<ex>es</ex></expan>
                <expan>an<ex>n</ex>uyties</expan> <expan>p<ex>ro</ex>fitt<ex>es</ex></expan>
                <expan>hereditament<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>good<ex>es</ex></expan>
                chattles money and <expan>Stock<ex>es</ex></expan> of mo[ney] may be <lb/>
                dulie and faithfullye imployed to and for such of the charitable uses and
                <expan>intent<ex>es</ex></expan> before rehearsed respectyvely for Which 
                they Were <add place="above">given</add> lymitted assigned or appoy[nted] by
                the Donors and ffounders thereof accordinge ti the purporce and true
                meanynge of the saide Statute <hi rend="bold">And therefore</hi> We 
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>aunde</expan> you that at <expan>c<ex>er</ex>taine</expan>
                [...] <lb/> and places Which you or any foure or more of you shall appoynte
                in this behalfe, ye or any foure or more of you doe make dilligent Inquirye
                and inquiryes uppon t[he] <lb/> <expan>p<ex>re</ex>misses</expan>, and all and
                singulerthe same and all other <expan>thing<ex>es</ex></expan> appoynted by
                the saide Statute for you or any foure or more of you to doe and execute,
                that ye or foure of you at the <lb/> leaste <expan>p<ex>er</ex>forme</expan>
                doe and execute With effecte in all <expan>poynt<ex>es</ex></expan> and in
                everye respecte accordinge to the saide statute and the true entent and
                meanynge thereof. And the same <lb/> <expan>Inquisic<ex>i</ex>on</expan>
                and <expan>Inquisic<ex>i</ex>ons</expan> anfd every of them together With all
                Decrees <expan>Iudgement<ex>es</ex></expan> orders and
                <expan>p<ex>pro</ex>ceeding<ex>es</ex></expan> Which you or any foure or more
                of you shall accordinge to the <lb/> saide Statute thereuppon make or sett
                downe. That you or foure or more of you have before us in out Chauncerye With
                all convenyent Speed. Or at the farthest in <lb/> Quindena Pasche nexte
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>ynge</expan> under the handes and Sealls of you or any
                foure or more of you and the <expan>hand<ex>es</ex></expan> and Sealles of
                them by Whome the same <expan>Inquisic<ex>i</ex>on</expan> and <lb/> 
                <expan>Inquisic<ex>i</ex>ons</expan> shalbe made together With this our
                <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>ission</expan>; <hi rend="bold">And we</hi> also 
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>aunde</expan> by aucthoritye hereof our
                <expan>Sheriff<ex>es</ex></expan> of our saide Cittye of Bristoll that at
                suche <lb/> tymes dayes and places as you or any foure or more of you shall
                appoynte them, they shall cause to come before you or anye foure or more
                of you such said as many <lb/> honest and lawfull mem of the saide Citye
                and Countye of the same, aswell Within <expan>lib<ex>er</ex>ties</expan> as
                <expan>W<ex>ith</ex>out</expan> by Whome the truthe in the
                <expan>p<ex>re</ex>misses</expan> may be before be known to <lb/> 
                inquyre of the <expan>p<ex>re</ex>misses</expan> uppon their oathes as you
                or anye foure or more of you shall require and <expan>com<ex>m</ex>aunde</expan>
                them; <hi rend="bold">Wyllinge</hi> alsoe and chardginge and <lb/>
                <expan>com<ex>m</ex>aundinge</expan> all and singuler our
                <expan>Justic<ex>es</ex></expan> of peace Mayors
                <expan>Sheriff<ex>es</ex></expan> <expan>Bayliff<ex>es</ex></expan>
                Constables headboroughes and all other our Officers Ministers and
                <expan>Subiect<ex>es</ex></expan> <lb/> to Whome in this case it shall or may
                appertaine, to be aydinge helpinge and assistinge to your our Saide
                <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>issioners</expan> or to any foure or more of you <lb/>
                in the due <expan>execuc<ex>i</ex>on</expan> of this our
                <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>ission</expan>. As they and everye of them tender our
                pleasure and will answere to the <expan>cont<ex>a</ex>rye</expan> att their
                uttmoste <expan>p<ex>er</ex>ills</expan>. <hi rend="bold">In wyntes</hi> Whereof we
                have caused these our <expan>l<ex>ett</ex>res</expan> of
                <expan>Com<ex>m</ex>ion</expan> to be sealled With our greate sealle
                <hi rend="bold">Wyntes</hi> our selfe at <expan>Westm<ex>inster</ex></expan>
                the eighteenth daye of <lb/> Julye in the Sixte yeare of our Raigne of
                England ffraunce and Ireland and Scotalnd the xli<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                <space/> <expan>p<ex>er</ex></expan> <expan>D<ex>omin</ex>um</expan>
                <expan>Canc<ex>ellarium</ex></expan> <expan>Angl<ex>ie</ex></expan> 
                virtute Statua; <space/> <hi rend="bold">Coppin.</hi>

            </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>